<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Intimate Partner Violence | ISSUES | The Ohio State University</title><link>https://issues-osu/issues/tag/intimate-partner-violence/</link><atom:link href="https://issues-osu/issues/tag/intimate-partner-violence/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Intimate Partner Violence</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><image><url>https://issues-osu/issues/media/logo_hu2fedd529b9d9d7008e9f6968cd645fa1_199187_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url><title>Intimate Partner Violence</title><link>https://issues-osu/issues/tag/intimate-partner-violence/</link></image><item><title>Craniofacial Injuries in IPV-Related Physical Abuse</title><link>https://issues-osu/issues/policy-briefs/ipv-craniofacial-injuries/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://issues-osu/issues/policy-briefs/ipv-craniofacial-injuries/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="overview">Overview&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Intimate Partner Violence (IPV) is a widespread public health crisis, and craniofacial injuries—including trauma to the head, face, and neck—are among the most common physical consequences. Many of these injuries involve brain trauma such as concussion, traumatic brain injury (TBI), or hypoxic-ischemic brain injury (HIBI).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>National emergency department data indicate that nearly 900,000 IPV-related visits occurred during the study period, with almost three in five involving craniofacial trauma. Female survivors experienced injury rates nearly five times higher than males, with the starkest disparities in early adulthood (ages 20–34).&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="policy-relevance">Policy Relevance&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Legal Context&lt;/strong>: Recognition of IPV-related craniofacial injury in statutes and clinical guidelines can improve survivor protections and treatment access.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Health Systems&lt;/strong>: Emergency medicine protocols should include screening for IPV in patients with head, face, and neck injuries.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Civil Rights&lt;/strong>: Survivors face barriers in healthcare and justice systems; data-driven policy is needed to reduce disparities in detection, treatment, and support.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="recommendations">Recommendations&lt;/h2>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>Mandate IPV screening protocols in emergency departments, especially for craniofacial injuries.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Expand Medicaid and social safety net coverage for long-term treatment of IPV-related traumatic brain injuries.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Increase funding for prevention and survivor support programs that integrate health and legal services.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ol>
&lt;hr>
&lt;h3 id="download">Download&lt;/h3>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="Policy-brief-001-head-IPV.pdf" download>Download the full brief (PDF)&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item></channel></rss>