<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Shockley-McCarthy | ISSUES | The Ohio State University</title><link>https://issues-osu/issues/author/shockley-mccarthy/</link><atom:link href="https://issues-osu/issues/author/shockley-mccarthy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><description>Shockley-McCarthy</description><generator>Hugo Blox Builder (https://hugoblox.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><image><url>https://issues-osu/issues/media/logo_hu2fedd529b9d9d7008e9f6968cd645fa1_199187_300x300_fit_lanczos_3.png</url><title>Shockley-McCarthy</title><link>https://issues-osu/issues/author/shockley-mccarthy/</link></image><item><title>Dr. Karla Shockley-McCarthy</title><link>https://issues-osu/issues/team/shockley-mccarthy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://issues-osu/issues/team/shockley-mccarthy/</guid><description>&lt;p>Dr. Shockley-McCarthy is a Research Consultant at the Government Resource Center, Ohio Colleges of Medicine.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Karla’s dissertation, School Social Work: Promoting Teacher Occupational Well-Being Through Teacher-Student Relationships: A Measurement Study, applies an exploratory sequential mixed-methods to develop a measure of teacher motivation and education system support to establish and maintain positive teacher-student relationships. Karla’s research presents the teachers’ perspective of factors affecting teacher-student relationships and provides the foundation for future interventions to support this vital component of teacher and student well-being. Karla also guides collaboration with The Ohio Department of Public Safety in efforts to enhance the psychological well-being of first responders’ children. Karla has 16 peer-reviewed publications in high-impact journals, including Social Science &amp;amp; Medicine, Child Abuse &amp;amp; Neglect, Trauma, Violence, &amp;amp; Abuse. She is the first author of three publications. Additionally, Karla has five manuscripts under review, 30 academic conference presentations, and 17 invited talks in the United States and the United Kingdom. Furthermore, Karla provides reviews for multiple peer-reviewed journals. She has extensive teaching experience, independently teaching six courses via in-person, hybrid, converged, and online course delivery modes. In addition, Karla is developing financial social work curricula and assisted with social work course alignment for accreditation purposes. A highly engaged leader, Karla serves on the Council of Graduate Students and various university committees at The Ohio State University, the Licking County National Advancement for The Association of Colored People (NAACP, Education Chair), and the Ohio Education Association Columbus Education Justice Coalition. Karla is expected to graduate in December of 2023.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>